Hello.
Welcome back.
In a section, we are going to see how to generate GPA your code using the SDM 32 for using the SDM
32 Kubi mix.
And then we go to Cube Idee and then write the code for it.
So I've opened my cubitt makes five over here.
But before we do the let's download the manual for the SDM.
Thirty two hall library hall stands for hardware obstruction layer h e l shall come over here and.
Over here and Google, you can just search SDM 32 Hall Drive driver Mindo, and then you select this
first link.
Right.
Click and then open in a new tab.
This first link that says SDM 32, that dot com.
You saw.
I know.
And then this.
And this.
The name description of SDM 32 F for Hall and L.
L drivers when you're right click it would open this PDA for you.
So we're going to.
We're going to save this.
This is going to be your reference for the functions that you can use to enable the various drivers.
So I'm gonna save this and then I'm I'm just gonna keep the name.
So I'll save it as it is.
Right.
It's saving.
OK.
So this is good.
One other thing.
So in this course, we will be using the, um, the SDM 32 F for one one new clue.
And Disko bought, um, the reason we use in the nuclear disco is because they have, oh, say, 90
percent of the upper for us are the same.
Apart from some 10 percent difference.
Well this, uh, this means is that the new clue has a U.
You can use the U out of the of the nuclear.
Without without adding an then or you know, f TDA to us.
B connector.
Whereas for the disco you have to extend all F TDA to us.
And the disco has a USP port that can allow us to program USP.
Oh TEGA USP devices.
Whereas the new clue hasn't got that.
However, the microcontrollers are the same.
They all have SDM 32 F for one one Feherty.
So the same quote should work on both ports.
Just that we may have to.
Well you don't have to pay for connected.
You may have to connect your own exten or device.
For instance, um, the ality on the new on the nuclear is connected to p a five.
I think by default LCD on the disk will be connected to other pins.
So you may have to setup those pings, but it's the same microcontroller.
Oh, you can just connect an entity to the p a five of your disco board.
If we are using the new clue in that particular lesson and the effect should be the same because the
microcontroller chip is the same.
Okay, so I'm going to come over here.
Uh, we'll stick here and then I'll go back to Google and I'm gonna search the, um, I think the user
guide for the board so that we can, uh, see the, um, the penult, how our peer fros, how well,
uh, our input output devices are connected, I should say.
So I'll say SDM thirty two for one one new clue.
User guide.
Then I hit Enter.
So there's this first link that says Estimated two new clue.
Sixty four Board User Guide.
All right, click from over here.
I don't know what this one says.
This is not a PDAF, this is a PDAF.
So we can take a look at the PDAF.
OK.
So does the user guide for the nuclear.
I'm gonna save this as well.
Whenever you are going to start a project, especially when it's a new board, you've got to get your
documentation ready.
So I'm starting this process with you.
I'm going to do the same for Disko.
So I'll change the word.
A new clue here to disco.
And then we have Discovery Kids, MCU, and it's a PDA.
So, right, click open in a tub and it's open and over here.
And there's the one for the disco.
Right.
All right.
Click Save.
Then I'll save this, so I've got a three documents, of course, one for each port.
And it may happen that you have different SDM, 32 boats.
You may, in fact, have the the, um, the F3 version or the F4 version, although things will be very,
very easy if we have the same boats so that you don't need to spend time converting things to your particular
port.
Okay.
So that being said, let's start off by creating the, um, input output.
Mm hmm.
Project.
So I'm going to come over here.
New project.
It's open
and it's brought me to the MCU selector.
You can come to this top four board selector so we can actually use the board selector.
I'm going to use the new clue here.
But you will be able to do this with a Disqus.
Well.
So I'm going to say SDM 32 over here.
F4.
And then over here.
Funny enough.
Yes.
Sean showing just the, um.
The discovery kids.
They're not showing the other ones for Hubble.
One one.
Okay.
So no problem over here.
When you search the air, search is not working perfectly.
They're not sure when the boards whose, um, reference modules, we just download it so we can come
back to MCU MP, you selecter this Pittaway come to this top and now we can search or see SDM 32 F for
one one.
And over here it tells me, you see there is no clue here.
And then there is this school here.
So double click this.
And this is it.
And it says this is active.
You can still buy pot for this particular port.
Nothing is deprecated here.
And it gives the, um.
It gives an overview of the components and the specifications of the board.
Once we are once we verify that.
Okay.
This the board we want, then we can click start projects.
But interestingly enough, it gives the market price here as well.
So if you're buying it from somewhere and the price is twice this price, you should know the person
is.
Yeah.
The person is over charging.
Okay, so click here to start a project, initialize all peripherals with default mode.
You can click.
Yes.
Over here.
Right.
It's open in.
Okay, it's open now.
So this is, oh, estimated it to four one one.
Like I said, this microcontroller is the exact same microcontroller on the disco board.
However, the schoolhouse connected more LCD and it's connected a push button at a different place.
And it's making use of the U.S. Pippin's for USP device configuration, et cetera.
So anything you write here should be the same for this school.
A new clue.
If you don't have that particular, um, I oh device connected, you may have to connect your own.
That is the only difference.
Okay, so this is our LCD.
It is connected to, um, a five us.
We can see over here.
We can zoom in here.
We can zoom in and you can click to drug.
You can click to zoom in, then click to drugs.
So it is the entity and we have our you outlines.
And just through these same lines that we program the board.
Okay.
So I'm going to clip in out.
What I'm going to do is come over here.
Obviously, this has been out and then we see a clip out.
Yes, sir, everything is cleared.
Okay, so we've cleared it.
So if you have a board from scratch like this and let's see the board, we didn't know where the, um,
the LDA and the and the pushbutton were connected.
We call to a user guide, which we downloaded.
It's over here.
So let's start with a nuclear first and then we take a look at a disco.
This is the disco kit.
There's the new clue.
A double click, this to open.
And it's opened.
And what I want to see is these schematic diagram of this port, and in case you want to create your
own SDM 32 microcontroller.
This a very useful document.
It gives you reference on how to design a circuit.
Okay, so I'm gonna scroll down.
It down here.
Okay.
Right.
So we're almost there.
Cuckoo slow over here.
Okay.
There's one here talks about the S-T linked debugger.
So we need the other document, the actual microcontroller.
Right.
So this is the microcontroller.
And it gives the penis.
So to find the push button on the microcontroller, we can see it from here.
This is the schematic symbol for pushbutton if we trace its connection.
We realize that is connected to P.c 13.
So we can enable the P.C 13 PIN as an input pin and we can just use this as a switch.
Wow, experiment.
And what you see over here is what is known as a sort of bridge.
If we want to disconnect P.S. 13 from this physical blue push button on our nuclear board, we can cut
off this bridge over here and you can find this sort of bridge under the board or on the board.
And it's labeled P. 17, S.P. one seven.
Right.
And the LDP, a five.
Over here.
This is Pier five.
How about the if not indicated is the LCD.
And I suppose because this schematic applies to all SDM 32 F4 boards.
Right.
So always is a four one one V.T..
There is F a four zero X X X as well.
So that is why it looks a bit generic.
Okay.
So this is the schematic.
It it's shown us where the push buttons and, um, the Kingdom X told us where the ality was.
So yeah.
But in case you end up with a um in the um in your normal life or in your everyday work, should you
find a document that is not showing everything.
You probably go back to the Internet and find another document that tells you exactly where the ality
is.
If we wanted to do that, we would do that.
But I already know where reality is.
So we can proceed with that.
Okay.
So this is that it was for the new clue.
Let's take a look at the disco board.
This team 32 Discovery.
Oh, double click to this.
And then what we want to see is the.
Is this schematic diagram as well?
OK, go slow.
OK, so this one is actually more straightforward.
Know, what I mean by that is they've indicated the simple power flows or the simple IO devices here
is telling this 2012.
This is page number 33.
Over here, it's indicating that maybe twelve is the P.
Twelve is the green ality on the discovery port.
Peaty 13 is the orange LCD PD.
14 is the red LCD.
Fifteen is the plurality.
So if we want to set these Eltis to blink, meaning said it must.
These are the the GPL your penis.
We need to interact with.
And the push button on the discovery board that is connected to me is zero.
So if one set a discovery board, if we want to set the, um, the push button as an input pin, then
we have to use pin number P zero.
Okay.
Right.
So we can go back to our Cuba mix and set our stuff.
So let's do some housekeeping stuff.
First, let's set what debug debugging o clock.
I'll come over here.
System clock and then I'll click system over here.
Debug the bughouse is zero wire over here and do not keep this the same RACC over here or just come
over here.
Uh, high speed clock.
I'll say bypass clock and then low speed clock.
I'll see crystal and ceramic resonator.
Right.
And then once that is done, I can close this and then.
Because I said I'm going to flush this onto the new clipboard.
I'm gonna be using the nuclear pin out.
So it's a p a five.
I'm gonna say this as GPL your output.
And then this we can rename over here by right click and then enter user name to rename again.
Right click enter user name.
So I'll simply give it a name.
Ellerby.
And now the name must change.
And we saw that the push button is connected to P.S. 13.
So let's find the easy 13.
Easy.
Thirty twelve is over here.
This is this is P.S. 13.
So this as GPA, your input.
And then right click and then I'll give it a name, DTN for Button.
Right.
So once we're done, we can actually go ahead and generally talk code.
So this is the clock configuration.
We can leave this the way it is.
And then we can come over here.
And then.
We can, um, we can give our project a location and then a storage forwarder, a place to store the,
um, the project.
I'm gonna give this a name.
I call this input output like this.
And then I'm gonna browse to change the location.
Let's see.
We've got a story to this forwarder.
A quick Pocan over here.
So the project name is Input Output, and I'll keep everything the same.
Over here, the toolchain we use and is the SDM 32 cube idee e.
If you're using a different to chain, you can select the appropriate one from this list.
So like this.
And before we do that, we can generate the report.
If we want, we can come to.
Let's see.
We can click over here, Gendre, to report, and then would you like to create a project?
First.
I can say yes to create a project and then the report has been generated.
We can click over here to open the folder.
So these are projects for them.
Where we saved our project.
The report comes in this text file as well as in P.D.A format.
And this has all the selections we made, including the date, the board type.
I know everything else.
Okay.
Um, I'll keep this open or minimize this.
Right.
So.
Okay, one other thing.
We can come to advance certains over here.
Let's see.
Is there something to change?
We can leave these the same as the over code generator.
We can see an April fool asset and this allows us to be able to check to offset or function is to see
what our functions have, the right parameters or argument to pass to them if they're wrong.
Argument is passed, is going to invoke something known as the asset function.
And this one he has set or free pins as analog.
And what this does is it helps save power.
And, um, I think in the four boards, the pins, the four status, the floating state.
And if you leave all of your pins floating, it takes more power.
So if a plane is not currently in use.
You have to set it to analog if you want to optimize for power consumption.
We're not using that.
So I'll leave it.
I'll come back to Project Hub of selected my two chain.
Everything is looking good.
I click over here to generate.
Write it down, generation.
We can say open food up to go to the foda, so there's the food.
That's where we started.
We can double click to open our project.
Oh, I'm opening to Cuba.
Max, I should have open the idea.
Um, yeah.
Right.
So.
So the icon that shows I.D., we can double click on it.
So double click this.
It's got no name.
I think there's a bug in the cube I.D..
Okay, so if you open this, you would select your default workspace.
You can keep it the same.
And then, um, you can just click to launch.
Okay.
Right.
So it's done open and can click here to expand, and it's even showing our PDAF over here.
We come to source.
We have our Mendo to see file over here.
Okay.
That's what we have.
So this is what is generated by the cube.
It makes its generator, the the clock configuration.
And then this initialize the GPL.
You according to what we chose.
As you can see over here, we have Ali Dippin cause we selected the LDP to be an output pin.
So we said it too early D.
And then the mood is output mode.
Push-Pull And then there's no pool over here with any set of speed cetera.
And we have that button also set us on inputs.
Been over here.
So for those of you taking this course, I assume you're familiar with how to initialize.
To set up the drive over a particular pair for you are just here to see how it is done in Cuba mix.
So I'm not going to spend time explaining each each member of the initialization structure.
What does it mean to be pain mode, et cetera?
I'll just give a surface overview of these.
I have a list for courses showing how to write your own drivers from scratch in assembly language in
A better to C and in C++.
No libraries used just from scratch.
So, yeah.
The purpose of this course is to show people who have taken those courses or who are familiar with these,
um, these techniques how to accomplish the same thing using the Cuba max generation.
So that is why we here.
Okay, so Cuba makes us generally to the functions for us.
So all we have to do is write the code to test it out.
So when we come over here, we have these comments that guide us, um, that guide us for, you know,
put in our code in particular areas.
For instance, it says this is where you put your use.
It includes from this side to decide.
Does Y says you saw code begin includes.
So if I want to do include.
And then I have my own dot h file.
I put it over here.
That is what Cuba makes once.
So it's got these blocks here for guidance.
Often I just clean them.
But you might find them useful.
So I'm gonna leave them there.
And when we come to our main function is start off by initialize in the hardware obstruction layer.
This is the hall.
And this is what allows us to use the whole library.
So this is initialized.
And then once that is done, it caused the system clock config function that we saw over here.
It is code.
So once this is done, then it would initialize our GPL u.
And it 's.
This is the execution of GPL.
You it.
Basically it's set in our button, pinned to input and then our early dippin to output.
Right.
So once this is done, we can go ahead and read the button and then talk it with reality.
So if we want to know which functions are available to us, then we can go to the whole library reference
module, which we downloaded earlier.
Right.
So let's see.
OK.
So this is the PDAF we downloaded earlier.
Gonna open it and I'm just going to press control and then F and then I'm gonna search GPI over here.
So I would jump straight to the aspect of GPL.
You can tell this is a reference document.
It's not meant to be read.
It's meant for references.
And one can tell this from the number of pages, a score of a one thousand eight hundred pages.
So you just have to come here and then get, you know, your reference.
So out of such GPA, you.
And then it will bring me to, um.
What does it say over here?
Says whole system.
For handlin GPA use.
Okay.
Oh.
Search of move to the next one.
Okay.
So this is what we want.
We want the section that talks about GPA, you.
Oh GPA you generic driver click over here would open.
And this one here talks about how the GPA you in its function is written by them, how the GPA, your
peers define the mode, etc. and then the GPA, you FAMM where API is over here.
It talks about how to use this driver.
We can read a bit.
It says enable the GPA you HP clock use in the following.
Right.
Using HARL racc GPA U.
X clock and enable.
And if we check the QB mix, Cuba makes us already done that for us.
Cuba makes us enabled a clock.
Okay, so basically this document deals with people, not people who want to write what Cuba makes generated
from scratch and then more.
So it says first enable this.
And then you've got to configure that pain mode, whether it's, you know, pull up, pull it, etc..
Cuba makes us done all of this for us.
And then GPL u haul G.
How gpl you innit.
This one here.
Initializes the GPL your function.
And then you can d initialize it as well.
So this whole GPL you in it is what Cuba makes refers to us and makes GPL you in it.
You see over here the function is how GPL you in it.
But when we go to our project over here, we don't find that.
We find M x gpl u.
S.
This is just to show that.
Okay.
This was written by Cuba.
Schmick's.
Right.
So yeah.
That's what it means.
But what is left out of this is how to read a pin and write the pin because we didn't tell the we did
until Cuba Amex or we cannot tell.
Cuba makes 10 to pin on for five seconds and then turn it off and then torgau this.
The logic is not part of the Cuba X generation.
So that is what we need to add over here.
It says I o operation functions.
And it says how the GPL you read it and then how GPL, your rights opinion.
And from these names one can tell.
We use them for reading and right into the pins and we have how GPL you told your pin.
So we can look at Repin.
So the function name is is this how GPL you read pain.
It takes the GPL.
You put this is this type the office of the GPL you put.
You have GPL, you sub X over here.
This X stands for the port.
It could be GPL, you A, B, C, D, et cetera.
So the first argument is the GPL you put in the second argument is that GPL, you pin and then it's
returns, GPL you state.
So if you call this function, how would you pay your read pain?
We have to pass the port and then the pin and then we going to get a state.
That's the return value of this.
And as you can see over here says the X stands for a two K.
Like I mentioned, the GPI U.
Port.
And the next function here says, how are you?
Right.
And this one here doesn't return anything.
It's a void.
Function returns void.
It takes two arguments.
Yeah.
It takes the um the I shouldn't say it's a void function.
I should just see it's returns void caused by saying that one might assume it doesn't take arguments
or talks.
Well, um, how gpl.
You're right.
I mean, it takes the GPL U.
Port.
And then it takes the GPL your pin and then it takes the state.
You want to write to the pin.
So how gpl your rights in the port that you pay your pin and then what you want to write.
High state or no states to the point.
That's what this does.
And then another interest in function, which is going to be your assignment, is going to be, um.
This one here, how GPL you toggle pin.
This one takes the port and then the pin.
You want to talk, you remember toggle this just to flip something.
Meaning if it's own, turn it off.
If it's off, turn it on.
So that's why you just need to.
The Dippin, you don't have to pass the state to talk, no function would get this state by itself and
then flip it.
So you just need to pass the port and then the pain of the port.
And we have other functions which you can take a look at.
Out of interest.
So now.
Right.
We know what we want to do.
We would simply want to read the pen, the push button, and then we write the state of the push button
to the reality.
Meaning if we'd read and the push button this is on, we want to turn the light on if it's off one or
turn off.
So let's run the experiment.
I'm going to minimize this.
Okay.
So we have this G.P.A. who has been initialised and what a great way to create a global variable here.
Call this you see you in eight on a score T or call this BOTTEN status or something.
Yeah, okay.
So then once this is done, I'm going to come into.
Just minimize this.
Once this is done, I'm going to come in to our main function here.
I'm going to come into our infinite loop while one over here just gonna clean these.
Goodness no.
I'm gonna clean these comments.
I think it's gonna be easier for you.
Yeah.
The reason I was hesitating is, yeah, some students complain.
I like cleaning comments.
Yeah.
Cause there is there's an older version of this course known as, um, Cuba makes four.
It's a free version.
And, um, it was the same process I open and then I clean comments trying to make the, um, the IDB
look much more clean and focused.
Turns out not everyone was happy with that.
Okay, so now we can get this is our entire main function.
You see, it's better like this.
It's clearer for the mind.
Okay.
So while one over here, what we want to do is call our whole GPL your read function.
So I'm gonna see how on the score cheapy I o underscore, read and then pin like this and then I'll
pass gpl u.
Over here.
What.
Um a pass.
What entity is connected to P.
A five hour pushbutton is connected to P.S. 13.
So what I can do actually is pass the um I could pass the name of the push-Button port.
I'm sure Cuba makes gave it a symbolic name.
You see, it's got a name here.
GPL U.
Port B10 GPL your port.
So it renamed the Port Port C to BTR and GPL your port.
Course we said PTM, should be a button peine so I can use this and we can find all of such names in
the main dot h file.
So just right.
Click over here and then um we can go.
We can open domain the H file over here.
We should be able to do the.
We can just say Togo source and header by right click in.
I should be here somewhere.
OK.
Torgau source slash header.
Okay, so this is the head of this Mendo H.
As you can see, BGN pain is just G.P.A..
You pin 13 BGN GPA, your port is just Port C, Ellie Dippin GPA, you pin five LDC GPA, your port
is Port B because we know ECPA five for the L.A. D.
Right.
So um, actually I'll copy this BITA and Port Y here controversy.
So we know our read our whole GPA, you read it takes the port and then it takes the um Dippin which
is BGN pin.
And then it would return to Penn State.
I'm going to store it in our forever that we created here.
So I'll see BGN status calls this.
OK.
So after this line execute, we would have the state of the push button stored in this very well.
So then we can come over here and call the how GPL your rights pin.
So we'll see how on a score GPL, you know, score.
Right.
And this one takes the takes the port as far as I can mount and the port we know is the lady port,
which is called Lady G.P.A. Port controversy to copy pasted over here.
The second argument is the, um, the pin, which is ality pin.
Let's get a name, a lady pin controversy to copy and pasted over here.
And then the state.
We want to write it up.
That's the third argument when a write to button state control see to copy and control V to paste and
close over here.
Right.
So this is it.
We can build and see how it works.
So we can click here to build.
Let's build in.
And it's built successfully.
We can click here to run or just click over here.
Depak.
I clicked on this blog here.
Right.
So so like this esteemed 32 Coatex M c, c plus.
Plus.
And it's going to open a debugger.
OK, first, we've got to edit the launch configuration properties.
So name input output debug.
You can keep everything here the same and say, OK.
Okay, so there's the debug the debug perspective or the debug view.
So if we want to run our code, we simply click the play button.
If we want to stop.
We click here.
If we want to step over.
Meaning two step.
Line by line.
We use these ones.
Step into.
Step into a function.
Step over to step over function.
Right.
If we want to enable in a few ways such as the disassembly view, the debug view, such as the disassembly
view, the watch window.
For those of you who are familiar with Carl Empty.
Okay.
And then i.e. are embedded workbench.
There is this window known as the watch window over here.
It is called the expressions view.
So we can come to window over here and sure view and we have all the views we have over here.
We have the memory for you.
If one enable that, we do just click to open it.
So a live expression is here.
This one here.
You can use it to watch your global variables.
So this is this expression over here.
Right.
So we can copy this.
I'll copy this.
And then I'll click add expression and then I'll pasted over here.
Right.
So let's run a while code and see what we have.
Open this.
This the value it guarantees here as you click the play button over here.
And the push button is one.
When I press it is zero.
Because the button.
I suspect it is octave high.
It is octave low.
I should say mean in its default state is high.
When you press it, go slow.
Right.
So basically, if you flush this onto your board, the LCD should be on because that button is on the
button as octave low.
When you press, then the button go slow.
You can see the watch window.
You can see over here, button status has changed.
Two value zero.
When I release it, it will go to one.
I've just released it.
I'm going to press again.
When I press, the elite goes off as well.
And then this becomes zero.
When I release, it becomes one.
Right.
So this is the, um.
This is it.
This is how simple it is to create inputs, outputs with the, um, the Cuba mix.
Okay.
So this all the risk for this lesson.
If you have any questions at all, just let me know and I'll see you in the next lesson.